A Finding Aid to the James Bassler Papers, 1969-2003, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
James Bassler papers
1969-2003
Archives of American Art
Bassler, James
AAA.bassjame
Archival Resource Key
3 Linear feet
The papers of fiber artist James Bassler measure 3 linear feet and date from 1969 to 2003. The papers consist of biographical material, correspondence, personal business records, writings, professional files, printed material, and five scrapbooks. Much of the material was assembled by Bassler as supporting documentation for tenure at UCLA.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Series 1: James Bassler papers, 1969-2003 (Box 1-3; 1.8 linear feet)
Biographical / Historical
Fiber artist and educator James Bassler (1933- ) is Professor Emeritus at UCLA. His weavings draw inspiration from Pre-Columbian, Andean, and Mexican textile traditions.
James Bassler was born to Margaret and Johnny Bassler, a major league baseball player who hooked rugs during the off-season. Bassler studied at University of California, Los Angeles where he would later teach from 1975 to 2000. Along with his wife Veralee, Bassler opened a crafts school in Oaxaca, Mexico in the early 1970s. Additionally, he established the fiber art program at the Appalachian Center for Crafts in Smithville, Tennessee (1980-1982) and was a summer faculty member at the Penland School of Crafts in Penland, North Carolina and the Arrowmount School for the Arts and Crafts in Gatlinburg, Tennessee.
Bassler and his wife Veralee live in Palm Springs, California.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited ot the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate copies requires advance notice.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
James Bassler donated his papers in 2003 as part of the Nanette L. Laitman Documentation Project for Craft and Decorative Arts in America.
Related Materials
The Archives also holds an interview of James Bassler conducted 2002 February 11-June 6, by Sharon K. Emanuelli, as part of the Nanette L. Laitman Documentation Project for Craft and Decorative Arts in America.
Scope and Contents
The papers of fiber artist James Bassler measure 3 linear feet and date from 1969 to 2003. The papers consist of biographical material, correspondence, personal business records, writings, professional files, printed material, and five scrapbooks. Much of the material was assembled by Bassler as supporting documentation for tenure at UCLA.
Biographical materials include resumes and writings about Bassler's father and siblings. Correspondence concerns exhibitions, lectures, projects, and Bassler's teaching career. Correspondents include Louise Allrich, Norman Cherry, Mildred Constantine, Kris Dey, Dominic Di Mare, Helen Drutt, Lillian Elliott, Betty Freudenheim, Teresa Huang, Eiko Ishioka, Ritzi and Peter Jacobi, Wojciech Jaskolka, Mi Koon Kim, Sherley Koteen, Gerhardt Knodel, Jack Lenor Larsen, Eudorah Moore, Gertrude Parker, Martin Peavy, Laurel J. Reuter, Ed Rossbach, and Paul Smith, among others. Among Bassler's professional files are items concerning his participation with the United States Department of State Art in Embassies program, his service as an expert witness for a legal case, and his teaching career at UCLA. One videocassette is a student's senior project. Five mixed media scrapbooks contain written statements, photographs of works of art, and printed material.
- James Bassler papers, 1969-2003; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1.8 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical materials include resumes and writings about Bassler's father and siblings.
  Correspondence concerns exhibitions, lectures, projects, and Bassler's teaching career. Correspondents include Louise Allrich, Norman Cherry, Mildred Constantine, Kris Dey, Dominic Di Mare, Helen Drutt, Lillian Elliott, Betty Freudenheim, Teresa Huang, Eiko Ishioka, Ritzi and Peter Jacobi, Wojciech Jaskolka, Mi Koon Kim, Sherley Koteen, Gerhardt Knodel, Jack Lenor Larsen, Eudorah Moore, Gertrude Parker, Martin Peavy, Laurel J. Reuter, Ed Rossbach, and Paul Smith, among others. Additional correspondence may be found in professional files.
  Among Bassler's professional files are items concerning his participation with the United States Department of State Art in Embassies program, his service as an expert witness for a legal case, and his teaching and administrative career at UCLA. One videocassette is a student's senior project and runs about 25 minutes in length.
  Printed materials include clippings, newsletters, and exhibition announcements and catalogs. Five mixed media scrapbooks contain written statements, photographs of works of art, and printed material. Also found are scattered photographs of works of art and a sketch of a working plan for a 14" by 14" hanging.
  - Biographical Material, Resumes, circa 1977-circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Material, on Bassler Family, 1996-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Valentines Sent by James and Veralee Bassler, 2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Correspondence, 2000-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Personal Business Records, 1970-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Writings, on Art and Artist's Statement, circa 1970s-circa 2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Professional Files, Center for Inter-American Relations, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Professional Files, Expert Witness, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Professional Files, Proposal for Group Exhibition, circa 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Professional Files, Teaching Files, 1978-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Professional Files, Teaching Files, Senior Video by Shai Hanuka, circa 1996; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Professional Files, US Department of State Art in Embassies Program, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Printed Material, Clippings, 1960s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Printed Material, Bulletins, Newsletters, and Press Releases, 1973-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Printed Material, Exhibition Announcements, 1970s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Printed Material, Exhibition Catalogs, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22-24)
  - Printed Material, Exhibition Catalogs, 1970s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
  - Printed Material, Reproductions of Works of Art, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Working Drawing, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, of Works of Art and a Parade, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook 1, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 3, 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Scrapbook 4, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook 5, Personal Statements, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)